A Guide to the Virginia State Library, Office of the State Librarian, Building Records, 1935-1941;
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia State Library, Office of the State Librarian, Building Records, 1935-1941
Library of Virginia
38904
2 cubic feet; five boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred to the Virginia State Library, date unknown.
Biographical/Historical Information
For many years, The Library of Virginia had no definitive home. Valuable early records were kept at Jamestown as early as 1676 and were then moved to the College of William and Mary for a brief period at the century's end. By 1780, extant records were moved to the Capitol in Richmond.
Coincidentally, in 1779, the Virginia General Assembly was presented among its legislation, "A Bill for Establishing a Public Library" drawn up by Thomas Jefferson. The bill provided for 2000 pounds yearly to be expended to maintain a State Library in Richmond. The facility was to be a reference library only without books being lent for home use. Perhaps ahead of its time, the bill failed to pass.
The Virginia State Library was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on January 23, 1823, to establish a public library with funds derived from the sale of William W. Hening's THE STATUTES AT LARGE. From 1823 to 1828, the Library was under the control of the governor and council. In 1828, the General Assembly created a joint committee on the library (located in a room in the southeastern corner of the Capitol) to oversee its administration. Use of the State Library was restricted to members of the state government in a policy that continued until at least 1856. The Secretary of the Commonwealth served ex officio as state librarian from 1832 to 1903.
The growth of the State Library was somewhat erratic. Book holdings increased from 1,313 in 1828 to 17,480 in 1856. Lack of funds and politics frequently intermingled to slow library development. General W.H. Richardson, State Librarian in 1852, became embroiled in an effort to remove him "to make way for some politician of democratic principles." At the close of Reconstruction, Dr. George William Bagby, then State Librarian, was terminated and his position abolished at the hands of Readjusters.
Eventually, on May 15, 1903, the General Assembly passed an act that created a library board to administer the library, authorized the deposit of public records in the library, provided for the publication of historical records by the library, and established a library fund for the purchase of books and private papers. The Library Board, which was responsible for naming the State Librarian, was itself appointed by the Board of Education. The General Assembly passed an act on March 29, 1944, transferring the power to appoint the Library Board to the governor.
While many public records somehow survived the Commonwealth's early years, many losses occurred due to fires, the ravages of war and negligence. When the library was moved, for example, in 1895 to a building separate from the Capitol, "chutes were constructed from the upper story of the Capitol to facilitate the delivery of books to the wagons of the junk dealer who had bought them." The move was poorly planned and the library's contents suffered great loss at the hands of those very authorities assigned to protect them.
The new facility quickly was found to be inadequate and efforts were made both in 1910 and 1920 to construct a proper building for the State Library and its collections. Ground was broken for the current facility on December 7, 1938. At last, on December 23, 1940, the newly completed Virginia State Library was opened to the public.
The Virginia State Library adopted the name, the Virginia State Library and Archives, in early 1987 to more adequately reflect its mission and purpose today. In July 1, 1994 the name was changed to The Library of Virginia. It serves as a general reference and research library, as the official repository of state archives and publications, and as a repository of state and federal documents. It provides assistance and advice to libraries around the state, and it administers state and federal library funds. The Archives and Records Division of the library administers the state records management program, arranges and describes records deposited in the division, and provides assistance and advice to state and local government agencies concerning the management of their records. Additionally, the agency produces many publications. The most notable among those regularly issued are the quarterly VIRGINIA CAVALCADE and the annual accession reports of the Archives and Records Division showing its most recent records and manuscript acquisitions.
Scope and Content
Contains documentation regarding the planning and construction of the Virginia State Library building at 11th Street and Broad Street in Richmond, including contracts and drawings.
Arrangement
Series 1: Building Commission Records, 1935-1941.
Contains correspondence, meeting minutes, mailing lists, and memoranda regarding the Commission's efforts to obtain a State Library building.
Series 2: Building Records, 1935-1941.
Contains written specifications and blueprints for the construction of the State Library building. Included are specifications for electrical systems and fixtures, photographic equipment, furniture, general library equipment, signage, heating systems, and sewer systems.
Some of the building records were previously accessioned as part of the Architectural Records Collection. Those accession numbers are indicated in parentheses in the folder listing for cross-reference purposes.
Oversize items have been separated and are housed in box 5.
Contents List
- Series 1: Building Commission Records, 1935-1941
  - Building Commission - Mailing lists, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Building Commission - Mailing lists, form letters, no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Building Commission - Members (general), no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Building Commission - Members: Robert K. Brock, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Building Commission - Members: Preston W. Campbell, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Building Commission - Members: S. Bernard Coleman, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Building Commission - Members: L. Preston Collins, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Building Commission - Members: Ashton Dovell, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Building Commission - Members: Mrs. Henry Fairfax, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Building Commission - Members: Wilmer L. Hall, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Building Commission - Members: Saxon W. Holt, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Building Commission - Members: Morgan R. Mills, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Building Commission - Members: Robert O. Norris, Jr., 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Building Commission - Members: George C. Peery, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Building Commission - Members: James H. Price, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Building Commission - Members: John B. Spiers, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Building Commission - Members: Robert B. Tunstall, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Building Commission - Members: Robert B. Tunstall, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Building Commission - Members: Roy D. White, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Building Commission - Minutes and expense vouchers, 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Building Commission - Minutes of committees, hearings, etc., 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Building Commission - Minutes of Executive Committee meetings, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Building Commission - Reports, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Building Commission - Resolutions, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Insurance Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - List of files, no date (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mailing lists, no date (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Snead bookstacks and library equipment, no date (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 2: Building Records, 1935-1941
  - Combined sewer in Capitol and Governor Streets at 12th Street for the State Library and State Library tunnel - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 4, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Electrical Fixtures; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 13, (Accession 33625) 1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Equipment specifications for the Virginia State Library, including book cleaning equipment and erasing equipment, fumigating equipment, photographic equipment, office equipment - Docket Va. 1331-F, (Accession 36631), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Equipment specifications for the Virginia State Library, including book cleaning equipment and erasing equipment, fumigating equipment, photographic equipment, office equipment; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, (Accession 36631), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Equipment specifications including aluminum furniture, chairs, special furniture, commercial furniture, miscellaneous, steel equipment, technical equipment, carpets, draperies, venetian blinds, miscellaneous - Docket Va. 1331-F, (Accession 36627), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Equipment specifications including the following classifications: aluminum furniture, chairs and special furniture, commercial wood furniture, miscellaneous, steel equipment, technical equipment, carpets, draperies, venetian blinds; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, (Accession 36627), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Specifications for bronze letters; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 26, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Specifications for electrical fixtures, (Accession 36625), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Specifications for Electrical Installation, (Accession 36626), 1939 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Specifications for electrical installation; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 8, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Specifications for fire extinguishers for the Virginia State Library; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 27, July 1940 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Specifications for heating, ventilating and air conditioning, (Accessions 36633 and 36674), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Specifications for heating, ventilating and air conditioning; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, (Accessions 36633 and 36674), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Specifications for photographic equipment; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 24, (Accession 36631), 1940 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Specifications for piping and auxiliaries to be installed in the central power plant of the State Library building, Aptil 1940 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Specifications for piping and auxiliaries to be installed in the central power plant of the State Library building; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 9, (Accessions 36628 and 36629), no date (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Specifications for piping and auxiliaries to be installed in the central power plant of the State Library building; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 25, (Accessions 36628 and 36629), 1940 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Specifications for the addition to the central power plant of the State Library building; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, (Accessions 36628 and 36629), 1940 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Specifications for the erection of a library building in Richmond, Virginia for the Commonwealth of Virginia; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 5, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Tunnel system connecting the Virginia State Library with the state power plant; Executed copy - Docket Va. 1331-F, Contract 6, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Proposed combined sewer in Capitol and Governor Streets at 12th Street for State Library and State Library tunnel, (From box 3, folder 1), April 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Specifications for electric eraser, (From box 3, folder 3), 29 March 1939 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Specifications for electric eraser, (From box 3, folder 4), 29 March 1939 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Inscriptions in Virginia State Library, (From box 3, folder 7), 22 April 1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Heating and ventilating diagrams, Virginia State Library, (From box 4, folder 2) 26 January 1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Piping in tunnel systems, State Library and Highway buildings, (From box 4, folder 5), October 1939 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Piping and auxiliaries to be installed in the central power plant, (From box 4, folder 6), April 1940 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Tunnel system for Virginia State Library, (From box 4, folder 9), May 1939 (Box 5, Folder 8)